Registar of the Poland. Polskie Sily Zbrojne miscellaneous records
Hoover Institution Archives
Registar of the Polskie Sily Zbrojne miscellaneous records
1940-1945
46036
Hoover Institution Archives
10 manuscript boxes, 22 envelopes (6.2 linear feet)
Poland. Polskie Sily Zbrojne.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1946.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
When World War II began, Polskie Siły Zbrojne (Polish Armed Forces) were outfitted with a fighting force that was approximately one million strong. The initial 1939 invasion by Germany on September 1st and then later the Soviet Union on September 17th resulted in the reformation of the Polish Armed Forces into three separate armies, spanning both eastern and western Poland: The Polish Armed Forces in the West, the Home Army (Armia Krajowa) and the Polish Armed Forces in the East. The collection of these divisions formed the whole of the Polish Armed Forces between 1940 and 1945.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection documents the activities of the Polish Armed Forces with a notable amount of materials focusing on the Armies’ activities in the Soviet Union. The collection is composed of correspondence, telegrams, memoranda, bulletins, reports, military orders and instructions, personnel rosters, lists, charts, photographs, and maps relating to the Polish Army in the East and in the Soviet Union, including the description of conditions and events in the Soviet Union. The collection provides details on the Polish civil and military personnel in the Soviet Union. It includes information on relations of the Polish Armed forces in the Soviet Union with the Soviet military command, and operations of various branches of the Polish Armed Forces in Eastern Europe and the Middle East.
Anders, Wladyslaw, 1892-1970.; Poland. Polskie Sily Powietrzne.; Sikorski, Wladyslaw, 1881-1943.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Poles--Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Eastern Front.; World War, 1939-1945--Deportations from Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Soviet Union.
- Supplemental PDF Inventory for Boxes 1-10, 1940-1945
  Scope and Contents
  The supplemental inventory is an item-level list of documents that appear in the collection: it encompasses correspondence, memoranda, pamphlets, reports, telegrams, bulletins, rosters, maps, charts, instructions and military orders. The list reflects the order in which each folder appears in a box as well as the order in which each document appears in a folder. Additionally, the inventory includes a short description on the topic that each document covers.
  Item Level Inventory
  Polskie Siły Zbrojne Inventory List
- Photographs
  - 139 prints depciting Polish military personnel and operations during World War II, 1940-1945 (Text A-D)
  - 11 prints depicitng the Polish Army in the USSR (Text E)
  - 15 prints depicting women in the Polish armed forces, 1940-1945 (Text F)
  - 34 prints depciting Polish military personnel and civilians in Africa and other foregin countires at the end of Wolrd War II, 1940-1945 (Text G)
  - 693 prints depicting Polish military personnel and military operations during World War II (Text H-P)
  - 50 prints depicting scenes in Warsaw during World War II (Text Q)
  - 46 prints depicting the Polish Underground movement during World War II and the Warsaw Uprising, August-October, 1944 (Text R)
  - 50 prints depiciting Captain Gutowski and his squadron in England (Text S)
  - 7 prints depicting Poles in concentration camps and displaced persons (Text T)
  - 46 prints depicting Polish statesmen, military officers, and dignitaries (Text U)
  - 91 prints depicting daily scenes in Poland, Polish citizens and various places of interest in Poland, ca. World War II (Text V)